World Psychiatric Association Records Finding Aid
Oskar Diethelm Library
World Psychiatric Association Records
1967 - 1989
This collection contains records from the World Psychiatric Association. The collection has 4 series: World Psychiatric Association Headquarters, Section on the History of Psychiatry, Newsletters, and Publications.
2.01 linear feet (5 boxes)
World Psychiatric Association
Oskar Diethelm Library DeWitt Wallace Institute of Psychiatry: History, Policy and the Arts Weill Cornell Medical College 525 East 68th Street, Box 140 New York, NY 10065
1989.0001
Dr. Eric T. Carlson was the first chairman of the Section on the History of Psychiatry of the World Psychiatric Association (WPA). Although the Section’s constitution was officially approved in 1971, Dr. Carlson and others were involved in its formation starting in 1967. The records of this Section during Dr. Carlson’s tenure have been maintained, and this library is not an official depository of the World Psychiatric Association. The majority of the other material was obtained during Dr. Carlson’s chairmanship of the Section on the History of Psychiatry.
There are no access restrictions on this material.
The World Psychiatric Association was founded in 1961 to form an association of National Societies of Psychiatry. According to the World Psychiatric Association, “The WPA is an association of national psychiatric societies aimed to increase knowledge and skills necessary for work in the field of mental health and the care for the mentally ill.” The purpose of the Association is to coordinate on a worldwide scale the activities of the member psychiatric societies and to advance inquiry into the etiology, pathology, and treatment of mental illness.
World Psychiatric Association; Carlson, Eric T., 1922-
This collection contains records from the World Psychiatric Association. There are 4 series in this collection.
World Psychiatric Association Headquarters: The World Psychiatric Association headquarters were located in Geneva, London, and Copenhagen at different times. The official records in this collection include statutes and bylaws, minutes of the Executive Committee (incomplete), some reports, and related material.
Section on the History of Psychiatry: The bulk of the correspondence in the WPA collection pertains to the Section on the History of Psychiatry. Dr. Eric Carlson began his relationship with the Section in 1967 as its first chairman. The constitution of the Section was officially adopted in 1971. Dr. Denis Leigh, Secretary General of the WPA in the late l960’s and 1970’s, was responsible for the organization of the symposia on different topics to members. According to Dr. Leigh’s specific instructions, the purpose of this Section was to further the study of the history of psychiatry through the meetings of expert committees, symposia, arrangement of lectures, and other educational events. The records of the Section consist of the Constitution, list of members, and correspondence pertaining to the planning of the Session on the History of Anxiety held at the V World Congress of Psychiatry in Mexico City.
Newsletters: Newsletters were published by the Secretariat and contain information about upcoming congresses and symposia, committees, individual and organizational members of the WPA, and related matters. A special issue (1986) is devoted to WPA history from 1961-1986 and contains the statutes and bylaws, as well as the Declaration of Hawaii, regarding ethical standards in psychiatry.
Publications: This series consists of The Bulletin, a publication containing newsworthy items and brief articles on WPA members. The series also contains programs abstracts from some of the World Congresses and symposia.
- World Psychiatric Association Headquarters
  - Statutes, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Extract from statutes of WPA bylaws, Undated (Box 1)
  - Organization and statutes, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Individual membership flyer, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Minutes of Executive Committee, 1968 - 1969 (Box 1)
  - Minutes of Executive Committee, 1970 - 1971 (Box 1)
  - Minutes of Executive Committee, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Minutes of Executive Committee, 1975 - 1977 (Box 1)
  - Draft of Declaration of Hawaii and cover letter, 1976 - 1977 (Box 1)
  - List of officers, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Report of the Secretary General, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Program of the 8th European Conference on Psychosomatic Research, 1970 (Box 1)
  - International Child Mental Health, Newsletter of the Child and Adolescent Section, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Christmas greetings, 1971 - 1975 (Box 1)
- Section on the History of Psychiatry
  - Constitution of the Section on the History of Psychiatry, 1971 (Box 2)
  - Memoranda on the Constitution of the Section, 1971 - 1974 (Box 2)
  - List of psychiatrists being considered for membership in the Section, compiled by Eric Carlson, c. 1971 (Box 2)
  - Members of the Section Committee on the History of Psychiatry, 1975 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence of the Section on the History of Psychiatry, 1967 - 1968 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence of the Section on the History of Psychiatry, 1969 - 1970 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence of the Section on the History of Psychiatry, 1969 - 1974 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence of the Section on the History of Psychiatry, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Notes of Dr. Carlson, Chairman of the Section, c. 1970 - c. 1971 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence of the Section on the History of Psychiatry, session on the History of Anxiety at 1971 WPA Congress, 1968 - 1970 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence of the Section on the History of Psychiatry, session on the History of Anxiety at 1971 WPA Congress, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence of the Section on the History of Psychiatry, session on the History of Anxiety at 1971 WPA Congress, 1971 - 1972 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence of the Section on the History of Psychiatry, session on the History of Anxiety at 1971 WPA Congress (Box 2)
  - Correspondence on Section on the History of Psychiatry, 1975 - 1976 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence on Section on the History of Psychiatry, 1977 (Box 2)
- Newsletters
  - Newsletters, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Newsletters, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Newsletters, 1970 - 1971 (Box 3)
  - Newsletters, 1972 (Box 3)
  - Newsletters, 1973 (Box 3)
  - Newsletters, 1974 (Box 3)
  - Newsletters, 1975 (Box 3)
  - Newsletters, 1976 (Box 3)
  - Newsletters, 1977 (Box 3)
  - Newsletters, 1978 - 1979 (Box 3)
  - Newsletters, 1981 - 1984 (Box 3)
  - Newsletters, 1985 (Box 3)
  - Newsletters, 1986 - 1987 (Box 3)
  - Newsletter – Special issue WPA 1961- 1986, Statutes and Bylaws Declaration of Hawaii/II (Box 3)
  - Newsletters, 1988 - 1989 (Box 3)
- Publications
  - Bulletin, 1968 (Box 4)
  - Bulletin written in Spanish, 1968 (Box 4)
  - Bulletin, 1969 (Box 4)
  - Bulletin, 1970 (Box 4)
  - Bulletin, 1970 (Box 4)
  - Bulletin, 1971 (Box 4)
  - Bulletin, 1972 (Box 4)
  - Bulletin, 1973 (Box 4)
  - Bulletin, 1974 (Box 4)
  - Bulletin, 1975 (Box 4)
  - Bulletin, 1989 (Box 4)
  - Program for Symposium on Anxiety, 1969 (Box 4)
  - Provisional program for symposium on Aspects of Anxiety, 1969 (Box 4)
  - Australian and New Zealand Journal of Psychiatry Studies of Anxiety II, Special Supplement, WPA meeting, Melbourne, May 1969 (Box 4)
  - Transactions of the Symposium on Schizophrenia written in Russian, 1970 (Box 4)
  - World Congress of Psychiatry abstracts, 1971 (Box 5)
  - General Program of World Congress of Psychiatry, 1971 (Box 5)
  - Inserts and related material for General Program for World Congress of Psychiatry, 1971 (Box 5)
  - World Congress of Psychiatry Program of Social and Cultural Activities, 1971 (Box 5)
  - WPA Regional Symposium – Symposium and Congress information and registration brochure, related papers, 1977 - 1978 (Box 5)
  - Psychopathology, “Physiological Basis of Anxiety” Symposium of the NPA, Section Clinical Psychopathology Vienna, July 11, 1983, 1984 (Box 5)